Hello, everyone, and welcome
to lecture 9 of CME 295.
So as today is a
kind of a special day
because we're having the last
lecture of the entire course.
So the menu for today
will be a little different
compared to usual.
We're going to try to divide
the lecture in three parts.
So in the first
part, we're going
to recap actually what we
did in the entire class
just to see how different
pieces kind of fit together.
In the second part,
we'll look at some topics
that are particularly
trending in 2025
and what we think are going to
be trending in the near future.
And then the third part will be
more way for us to just conclude
and next steps for all of you.
Does that sound good?
Cool.
So with that, we're going to
start with the first part, which
what I mentioned is
about recapping what
we did this entire quarter.
So nothing new here
is just a way for us
to piece everything together.
So if you remember
a lot of weeks ago,
I believe it's like
maybe 10 weeks ago,
we had lecture 1, which was
focused on understanding
what transformers were.
So at the very
beginning of the class,
we didn't even how we
could process text.
So I guess the
first step that we
saw was this tokenization step,
which consists of dividing
the input into atomic units.
And so here, the way
we divide the text
is something that is
arbitrary in some sense.
So we have different algorithms
that allow us to do that.
And we saw that the most
common tokenization algorithm
is the subword level tokenizer.
And we saw that some
of the advantages
were that roots of words
could be reused and leveraged,
especially when it came to
representing those tokens.
And speaking of
representation, once we
were able to divide the input
text into atomic units, a.k.a.
tokens, the next step
for us was to learn how
to represent these embeddings.
So if you remember, we
saw some methods that
were very popular back then.
So one of them was
called word2vec.
And the representation was
learned from a proxy task, which
was something like
predicting the center word
or predicting the context words.
But then we saw that this way
of learning representations
had some limitations,
one of which
was that these representations
were not context aware, meaning
that if a word is
in a given sentence
or in another sentence,
that word will
have the same representation
in both sentences.
And so for that reason, we saw
some other methods that were
popular in the 2010s, one of
which was RNNs, if you remember.
So RNNs had this
recurrent structure,
which processed
tokens one at a time
and kept an internal
representation
of the sequence so far.
But then we saw that
a big limitation
of this problem of
long range dependency,
and in particular,
the fact that tokens
that were encoded
far in the past
were not quantities that
were able to be kept I guess,
as the sequence got longer.
And this is the
reason why we saw
the central idea of
this whole class, which
is the idea of self-attention,
where tokens can actually attend
to one another
regardless of where they
are placed in the sequence.
So you can think of
this as a direct link.
And so this, for
instance, is what we saw.
We saw that there are three main
terminologies that people use.
So query, key, and value.
So typically want to
how similar a query
is compared to the
keys in the sequence.
And you quantify that by
taking some dot products that's
kind of scaled and softmax.
And then you have the
corresponding value
that is taken.
So at the end of the
day, we obtain some kind
of weighted average of all the
tokens that are in the sequence.
And then you may also be
familiar now with this formula.
So softmax of qk transpose over
square root of k times v. So
this is the matrix formulation
of what I mentioned here,
which is able to process
these computations in a very
efficient way.
And it's something that today's
hardware is well equipped to do.
And then we finished
the first lecture
by going through the
architecture that
is the foundation of modern day
LLMs, which is the transformer.
And we saw that there
are two notable parts
in the transformer.
So one was the encoder in
the left part of the figure.
And then the right
part is the decoder.
And we saw how this was applied
in the case of translation.
So at the end of
the first lecture,
we saw what motivated us to
end up with the transformer.
And we saw that transformer
was working quite well
in the case of translation.
And so in the next
lecture, what we
saw what were the
little improvements
that people have made
to this architecture
since it was released.
And if you remember,
it remember,
it was in 2017 that
it was published.
So one particular improvement
that people have made
is in the way we
consider positions,
because in the original
transformer, paper,
positions were encoded
in an absolute way,
as in each position
had its own embedding.
And this embedding was added
to the token embedding.
But then if we think about
it, positions, actually, we
don't really care about
the absolute position.
We care about the relative
position between tokens.
And in particular,
we care about how far
tokens are in the self-attention
computation, which
is why we saw this method
that is now quite popular
called rotary position
embeddings, a.k.a., rope
that is now quite used.
And it is a method that rotates
query and keys, both of which
happen in the
self-attention computation.
And so here what
is quantified here
is purely a function of
the relative distance
between two tokens.
And not only that,
it is something
that is taken care of in the
self-attention layer, which
is what we care about.
So this was one big improvement.
And then we saw some other
improvements, especially when
it came to how the
multi-head attention
layer-- multi-head attention
layer was composed of.
And in particular, we
saw that it was possible
for us to have some groupings
of the matrices that we learn.
So we don't need to have
one matrix, one projection
matrix per head for, let's
say, keys and values.
We can actually group them.
So this is for instance,
what is mentioned here.
So group query attention.
And then we also saw
some other techniques
that I have not
represented here,
for instance, the normalization
layer in the transformer which
here happens after
each sublayer.
But I guess nowadays people have
tried moving the normalization
piece before the sublayer.
So here it's the
post-norm version.
And then before
the sublayer part
is called the pre-norm version.
And then the last
thing that we saw
was that from this transformer
former architecture,
there are a lot
of derived models
that were based from that.
So we saw that if we only
keep the encoder part,
we could compute very
meaningful embeddings.
If you remember,
there was this kind
of landmark paper on
encoder only model, which
is BERT, which was heavily used
in the context of classification
because it relied on the encoder
embedding of the CLS token.
So that was one.
But then we also
saw that there was
a number of other kinds of
models, all more or less derived
from the transformer.
So you could only keep the
encoder, which was for BERT.
You could only keep the decoder
just, for instance, for GPT.
And you could also
have both, which is
for instance, the case of T5.
And one particular aspect
of each of these models
is that encoder only is
not able-- in the way
that we saw-- is not
able to generate text,
but it's able to generate
embeddings which can
be used for downstream tasks.
But then encoder
decoder models like T5
or decoder only
models like GPT, they
can be autoregressive
and generate texts.
The paradigm can be
text in, text out.
And with that, we then focused
on what now everyone calls
large language models,
which are transformer
based models, specifically
text to text models.
So decoder only
transformer based models.
And we saw that people have
come up with a lot of new tricks
now because these models,
as the name indicates,
people have scaled them up.
But then one question
was kind of thrown,
which is do you actually need
all these parameters to just do
a forward pass.
So we saw one kind
of variant which was
based on a mixture of experts.
So what mixture of experts are
is instead of running everything
through the whole
entire model, you're
going to instead have
a number of experts
that you're going to
activate in a sparse way.
So for instance, for
one input, you're
going to just activate
just a subset.
And then for
another input you're
going to activate
another subset so
that you don't need to do all
the computations all the time.
And we saw that this
mixture of experts, they
were used in LLMs, in particular
in the feedforward neural
network layer.
So here you would
have experts as being
different feedforward
neural networks.
And you would have
a gating mechanism
that would reroute to
the correct feedforward
neural network.
And then we also saw that
some papers were also
able to produce some nice
visualization in terms, I guess,
which token gets routed to which
expert, because this routing,
we saw that it was done
at the token level.
And so one reason why it's
done at the token level
is to be able to, I
guess, smartly put
the experts on different pieces
of hardware, different GPUs,
and then parallelize the
computation a little bit more.
And then we also
saw that these LLMs,
they always are tasked with
predicting the next token.
And in order to
predict the next token
we were interested in, I
guess, how we were doing this.
And so one particular method
that people use is just sample.
Sample from the
output distribution.
So you have let's
say given an input
you have a distribution
of probabilities of what
the next token would be.
That is output by the model.
And what you do is
instead of let's
say taking the highest
probability, which
is called the greedy kind of
decoding, you actually sample.
So it introduces some
randomness and allows the model
to produce kind of a bigger
variety of kinds of outputs.
And we saw that you could
adjust how much, I guess,
a variety you want in
your outputs by tweaking
a hyperparameter
called temperature.
So very low temperature leads
to very spiky distribution.
So more deterministic outputs
and higher temperatures
are, I guess, a bit more
random, a bit more creative.
So until then, we
saw what LLMs were,
how they were based on the
transformer, how they connected
to the architecture that we
saw in the first lecture.
And then in lecture 4, we
saw how people actually
trained those LLMs because as I
mentioned, these LLMs are large.
And so you cannot naively
fit them in your hardware.
You need to be a little
bit smart about it.
So in particular, what people
have noticed in the early 2020s
is that the bigger your model
is, the better your performance.
And so people just
started building
bigger and bigger models.
So here in the illustration
we saw that-- so on the y-axis
is the Teslas.
So the lower the better.
So we saw that the more compute
you use, the better your test
performance.
And same with increasing
the data set size.
the number of parameters.
But then as you know
compute is not infinite.
So there was a
natural question that
came out of the community which
was if we give you a given
budget, a given compute budget,
can you choose, I guess some,
quote unquote, optimal
number of parameters and data
set size on which you
want to train your model.
And so we saw that there was
this paper that was published
in the early 2020s,
which actually studied
the relationship
between, I guess,
if you vary the data set size
and the size of your model
and the performance
on the test set.
And then we saw that actually,
most models at the time
were what we say
undertrained because they
were too big compared
to the data set
that they were trained on.
The data set that
they were trained on
was not as big as
they should have been.
And so in particular, there
was a kind of a rule of thumb
that came out of this, which
was if you have a given
number of parameters
in your model,
you should at least train
it on 20 times the number
of parameters in
terms of tokens.
So for instance, if you have
a 100 billion parameter model,
you should train it on at
least 2 trillion tokens
because the 2 trillion
is 100 billion times 20.
So that's the rule of thumb
that people have used.
And then as I
mentioned previously,
these models are huge.
So people have
tried to also make
the computation more efficient.
And so there was this
method that we saw,
which is actually
quite important
called flash attention.
And flash attention
is a method it
that leverages the strength
of the underlying hardware.
And in particular, it
looks at-- so GPUs, more
particularly-- it looks
at the kinds of memories
that a GPU has.
So it has a big, but slow memory
and a small, but fast memory.
So the HBM and
SRAM respectively.
And we saw that
this method tries
to minimize the number of reads
and writes to the big and slow
memory, to the HBM.
And so the way it
was doing this was
to divide the computation
in little bits
that it would send
to the SRAM, which
is the small but fast memory,
so that it can do the end
to end computation
and then send it
back to where it was in order
to do the full end to end
computation.
So that method is
an exact method,
meaning that we're not doing any
approximations to the results.
But it led to
significant speedups.
And in particular, there
was this second idea
from the paper, which is
a kind of an important one
as well, which was that
sometimes it's OK for you
to not store results.
It's OK for you to just throw
them out and then recompute
when you need them again.
So there is this
idea of computation
using what I described,
which led to faster runtimes,
even though we were
doing more computations.
So that was flash attention.
And we also saw a
number of other methods
that were meant to, I guess,
parallelize the computation.
So we saw data
parallelism, which
was this idea of not having
all your data be processed
on a single GPU, but instead
divide it into multiple places.
And then we had
the second method,
which was model parallelism,
where even for a given forward
pass, you would actually
involve multiple GPUs.
So anyway, there were a lot of
very interesting techniques,
a lot of different
ideas about how to train
this model in an efficient way.
And in particular, so
what I described here
is mostly important for the
first step of the training
process of an LLM, which is
called the pre-training, which
is meant to teach the model
about the structure of language
about the structure of codes.
And in particular,
this model was trained
with huge amounts of data.
So think about
trillions of tokens
or even tens of
trillions of tokens.
And so that first step goes
from an initialized model
to a model that is
able to autocomplete
because it is trained with
an objective of predicting
the next token.
So at the end of
this first stage,
you have a model that
knows how to autocomplete,
but you have a model that is
not very helpful because it only
knows how to complete things.
So in order to have the model
be useful for our use cases,
we had this second step, which
is called the fine tuning
step, where we teach
the model on the kinds
of input/output pairs that
we wanted to perform well.
So this is also called the
SFT stage supervised fine
tuning stage.
And at the end of
this second step,
we have a model that not only
knows the structure of text
and codes, but also is able
to behave in the way you want.
But so far, up
until step number 2,
we have only taught
our model what to do.
We have not taught
it what to not do.
And this is why we had our third
step, which was the preference
tuning step, where we
took our model that
went through the
pre-training stage, that
went to the SFT stage.
And now we want to inject
some negative signal
as well as in I want
you to prefer this
compared to this output.
And this third step
uses preference data.
So like the name suggests,
so preference tuning uses
preference data which is
typically pairwise data where
humans say I prefer this
output compared to that output.
And typically, the model here is
able to align the kind of output
it produces with
human preferences that
could be along the
dimension of usefulness,
of safety, friendliness, tone.
There's a bunch of
different dimensions.
But yeah, so that's what is
happening in this third step.
And in this third step,
it's actually in lecture 5
that we dug into what
that third step was about.
So if you remember, we had
drawn a parallel between the way
our LLM produces tokens.
And I guess what people in the
reinforcement learning field,
I guess, consider how a
given policy is interacting
with some environments
and performing some action
and being in some states.
And the reason why
we drew that parallel
was to be able to leverage some
RL-based techniques in order
to train our model.
So in this case, we said our LLM
is a little bit like a policy.
So given some state,
which is the input
it has received so far, it
can perform the next action.
And in this case, it is
to predict the next token.
And this prediction is made
in the environment of tokens.
And when we predict a
completion, what we do
is, at the end of the day, we
have some signal, some reward,
which can be the
human preference.
So this is the parallel
we drew with the RL world.
And with that in mind,
we talked about rewards.
But the problem is
that rewards are
only available for a limited
set of data, which is why
we saw how to model rewards.
So we saw this formula.
If you remember it's called
the Bradley-Terry formulation,
which models how the probability
of an output being better.
Another one is as a function
of, I guess, two scores,
like the score of output I
and the score of output J.
And we saw that
reward models, they
are typically trained by
having this formulation in mind
in a pairwise fashion.
So what this means is a reward
model, you give it two outputs.
You say this one is
good, this one is bad.
And then I want you to
say this one is good.
You train it in a
pairwise fashion.
But then your model is actually
predicting always two scores.
It's always predicting
the score RI
for output I, RJ for output
J. And so at inference time
you're only giving
it one output.
So I think that's one subtlety.
We train it in a pairwise way.
But at inference time, we're
using it in an individual way,
if that makes sense.
And so once we trained
our reward model using
this formulation, then
we were able to use
it to steer our LLM towards the
direction that we care about.
So if you remember, the
way we steer our LLM
in the direction of
human preferences
is to give it a
prompt so that it
can produce a completion,
a.k.a., a rollout.
Or in simpler terms, an answer.
And then we take this
prompt, we take this answer.
We put them both in the
reward model that tells us
how good the model response is.
And depending on what
the reward model says,
we can tune the
weights of the LLM
in a way that maximizes human
or the reward that we saw,
which is trained on
human preferences.
And the last function
of this RL setup
is typically
something that tries
to maximize rewards, but also
keep the model close to the base
model.
And here, by base model,
we mean the SFT model.
And the reason why we want
that is because this reward
is imperfect.
So we saw this phenomenon
of reward hacking
where your reward
can be imperfect.
And the LLM can exploit
its imperfect nature
to tune it in a way that
actually does not align
with what you want it to be.
So you want the LLM
to not be too far
from the base model, which is
actually already a good model.
So it's a way to regularize
that if you want.
And you also want
the iteration updates
to not be too big either.
So you typically have
these two constraints.
You don't want it to deviate
too much from the base model,
but you don't want it to deviate
too much from the previous RL
iteration.
And then just as a
reminder, I think
this was lecture 5 I think was
the most technically challenging
of the whole class.
So completely fine
if the first time
you were like, what's happening.
But hopefully now, it should
be a little bit more clear.
Cool.
And then after lecture
5, we're like, OK,
we've done a lot of hard work.
So the good thing
is we're in 2025.
And in the past 12
months, or now 14 months,
we've seen a lot
of models that were
being released with these
reasoning capabilities.
And the way they were trained to
exhibit these advanced reasoning
capabilities was
actually leveraging
a lot of the techniques
that we saw in lecture 5,
just like RL based techniques.
And in particular, what
we want our LLM to do
is to output a reasoning
chain before producing
the final answer.
And the reason why
we wanted to do that
is because people have
seen that it improves
the performance of the model.
And so it's actually relying on
this idea of chain of thoughts,
which I believe we saw
at lecture 3, which
is a prompting technique to have
your model output the reasoning
before outputting the response.
So long story short, up
until lecture 6 our LLM
was having a prompt as input,
directly outputting the output.
But in lecture 7, we said--
sorry, in lecture
6 we said, well,
let's have our LLM
actually first output
a reasoning chain that
the user may or may not
have access to before
outputting the final answer.
So you want to teach
the LLM to do that.
So how do you do that?
Well, first before
doing this, I just
want to show you this
chart, which we saw,
which is the
performance of the model
as we're teaching it to
produce these reasoning chains.
So people have typically
measured the improvement
in performance by comparing it
to, I guess, certain benchmarks.
And this one is a popular
one, the aim benchmark,
which is a math benchmark.
And we saw that as the
training progresses,
the accuracy number
of guess what
the LLM outputs is increasing.
But back to what I was saying.
The key technique that we
use to teach the model how
to output these reasoning chains
is leveraging the RL techniques
that we saw in lecture 5.
And in particular,
up until now, we
saw PPO was the main RL
algorithm that people were
using up to maybe last year.
And now people are kind
of prioritizing GRPO
as an RL algorithm in order to
teach the model to be better
at reasoning tasks.
And there are several reasons to
that I will explicit right now.
So we saw this illustration
that compared how
GRPO was differing with PPO.
And if you can see
in the graph, there
are a few things
that are different.
The first thing is that GRPO
does not rely on a value model.
So who remembers what
the value model is?
Yep.
Yes, exactly.
So the value function
is trying to predict
what the reward would
be if you were to follow
the policy of the LLM.
And I guess it's a way to
have some baseline as to how
good some predictions are.
You want to make
it more relative.
So the value function
is a way for us
to make these rewards
a little bit more
relative to one another.
And so that's how
PPO was doing this.
So it was having
a value model that
was making these predictions.
And then we had these
generalized advantage estimation
method that was combining
the rewards predictions
with the value
function predictions
in order to have what
we call advantages.
So advantages is how
good's your output
is compared to some baseline.
But then in contrast
to that, GRPO
said, OK, today, we don't
need a value function
because it's too expensive
to train to maintain
what we're going to do instead.
Is generate several
completions, and then
have some formula that compares
the rewards of these completions
to one another.
So it's going to have some
relative effect in a sense
that it will make
things more relative.
And in doing so you're actually
not needed to maintain and train
a value function.
And that's one big
difference compared to PPO.
And the second big
difference, which
is not represented
in this illustration,
is that GRPO is
typically an algorithm
that people have used in the
context of teaching your model
to be better at reasoning tasks.
And so we saw that
these kinds of problems
have a verifiable reward
because when you complete a math
problem, you actually know
the answer you need to get to.
So you don't need to train
a reward model to tell you
how good your final answer
is, because you already
know the answer.
And so we saw that
GRPO was in particular
used in the context of when
you actually don't even
need reward model,
when you actually
have a verifiable reward.
So at the end of the day, the
only two models you need to keep
are the policy model
and the reference model
to be able to just compare how
far you are from the reference
model.
Cool?
I know this one was also
a challenging class.
I guess, so far so good.
And this is also on the final.
So which is why
I'm taking things
more slowly for this
second part of the recap.
So is everything good so far?
Yeah?
Perfect.
We also saw some
extensions of GRPO.
So if you remember, there
was some kind of bias
that was a result of the
loss function of GRPO having
some normalization term
that penalized tokens
that were in shorter outputs.
So we saw that if you use
GRPO in its original case,
in its original form, we saw
that after a certain point,
the algorithm will incentivize
your model to produce
longer and longer answers.
Longer and longer
incorrect answers.
And the reason why
it does that is
because relative to
short, incorrect answers,
it penalizes less long
incorrect answers.
And so this is the reason
why there are some extensions
that people have worked
on this year, one of which
was GRPO done right.
So we saw that they basically
removed the normalization term.
And there was another method
that we saw which was called
DAPO, D-A-P-O, which
also had some variants.
And that's for reasoning models.
And then lecture
7, we had a model
that we knew how to train it.
We knew how to use it
for reasoning tasks,
how to train it to be better.
But now we wanted the model
to be useful and interacting
with outside systems.
So we saw one technique that is
kind of an essential technique
called RAG, short for retrieval
augmented generation, that
is meant for you
to be able to fetch
relevant documents from
some knowledge base
in order to answer a
question, or answer a prompt.
And the reason why
you want to do that
is that the
knowledge of your LLM
is including up to the data that
is up to the knowledge cutoff
date, which is the max dates of
what your LLM has been trained
on.
And from a practical
standpoint, I
guess from what we see nowadays,
you're typically not training
your LLM daily or continuously.
And so in cases where
you need your LLM
to about things that
happened recently
or about things
that happened that
were not in your
LLM training data.
You want your LLM to have
access to such information.
And so that's how
RAG is very useful.
So we saw that RAG
depended very heavily
on the way it retrieves data.
So we saw that the
retrieval part was mainly
composed of two steps.
So the first one was
candidate retrieval,
which uses bye encoder
kind of setup where air.
You're basically doing
some semantic search.
So you're computing the
embedding of the query.
You have some
pre-computed embeddings
of the documents in
your knowledge base,
and you're taking the ones that
maximize some similarity score.
Let's say some
cosine similarity.
So this first step is allowing
you to retrieve, I guess,
a filtered version of
the potential documents.
And then typically,
you have a second step,
which is called ranking--
or reranking because
the first step already
gives you a ranking--
which has typically a
more sophisticated setup.
So it's a cross encoder kind of
setup where you have your query
and your document that
are both fed to some model
and produces a
more precise score.
And then you use this final
score to rank the final results.
And you typically choose
the top, let's say, k.
And then you add
them to your prompts.
So it's the augmented part.
So retrieval is everything
I mentioned so far.
And then once you have
the relevant documents,
you add them in your prompt,
which is the augmented part.
And you generate the answer.
So the reason why I'm
taking so much time on RAG
is RAG is such an
important concept.
Also, if you were to
have interviews or also
maybe in the exam who knows.
So I think it's an important
concept to have in mind.
The second one that we
saw was tool calling.
And tool calling is allowing
your LLM to leverage tools.
The way it does that
is in two steps.
The first step is for your
model to which API there
is out there, at the end
of which your LLM says,
OK, I want to use
this API and I want
to use it with these arguments.
And then you have an
intermediary step,
which is you just run your
API with these arguments.
And then the second
step is you feed
the results of
this operation back
to the LLM, which then
produces a final answer.
So that's how tool
calling works.
So if you say to your
LLM, you can use this API,
this is how your LLM
would leverage that.
And then we saw that modern
day agentic workflows
we're leveraging both RAG and
tool calling as key methods
to perform actions.
And we saw an
example, data example,
which was such that
you had some inputs.
And then your LLM had a
series of different calls
in order to perform some action.
And then at the end of
it, it retrieves-- sorry,
it returns an answer.
Cool.
And then last
lecture, we saw how
we could evaluate LLMs,
which is a much tougher thing
to do now that LLMs can do
a bunch of different things.
So we first saw that there
was some rule based metrics
that people were using before
LLMs came into play, metrics
that you may have heard like
BLEU, ROUGE, METEOR, and so on.
But the main limitation
was that they were not
considering how language could
differ, but still be correct.
And so this key idea that we
saw was why not leverage LLMs
to evaluate outputs.
And so there is
this key idea of LLM
as a judge where you receive
as input the prompts.
The model response
along with the criteria
that you want the response
to be evaluated on.
And then you want your
LLMs to output two things.
The first one is a rationale
for why a given score is outputs
along with that score.
So nowadays, LLM as the
judges are typically
outputting a binary
response, either pass
or fail, true or false,
just because it's easier.
And we're also
having the rationale
be output before the score,
because in practice it's
something that also improves
the performance of the LLM
as a judge.
A little bit if you want,
like reasoning models
do, by outputting
the reasoning chain
before they output the answer.
But then we also saw that
there were some biases that
came with this approach.
We saw a position bias,
which is the way you present
the LLMs to compare matters.
So if you present
something first,
then maybe the LLM will
just prioritize that first.
So there's position bias.
There was verbosity bias, which
is your LLM just preferring
longer outputs.
And self-enhancement bias
was another one where
it prefers its own outputs.
And then we also saw
a number of benchmarks
that people use
nowadays in order
to say how great their LLM is.
So if you see the
releases that come out,
there are typically
a bunch of metrics
across a number of
different benchmarks
that people know about.
So that spans
knowledge, the ability
to reason coding, which is
very important because a lot
of applications are coding
related, and then safety.
And then this is not
an extensive list.
So there's actually
many more dimensions.
So yeah, I think that's
where we stopped.
And it was last lecture.
And this is all you're
expected to know for the final.
Everything after that is not
going to be part of the final.
Any questions on this so far?
Cool.
I'm expecting 100 for
everyone for the final.
But yeah, I would say,
what I went through
is going to be
foundational for the final.
So I guess if you understood
everything I said,
I think you're going to
be ready for the final.
So, yeah.
But if you have any
questions, Shervine and I
are always here to--
oh, yeah.
You have a question.
Yes, so the question is the
scope for the final lecture
5 to lecture 8.
Yes.
So for midterm, it was
lectures 1, 2, 3, 4.
And this one is 5, 6, 7, 8.
So I guess it's equal size.
Cool?
OK, great.
So with that said,
we just finished
recapping this entire
quarter worth of lectures.
And now we're going to go to
the second item of today's menu,
which is looking at
some trending topics.
And so I'm going to
start with the first one.
And I'm going to
introduce it as follows.
So if you remember, we
saw that the transformer
was a concept and
an architecture that
was first introduced in the
context of machine translation.
So it performed great.
People said, OK, it performs
great on machine translation,
why not try it on
other text tasks.
So they tried it.
Performed great.
But now the question
is, can you not use it
for things other than texts.
It's a natural question.
So in order to
answer that question,
I just want us to
remind ourselves
that this architecture is
relying on this concept of self
attention.
And this is what is making
the transformer work so well.
So if we just recap
what self-attention is--
this illustration kind of
does the job quite well--
you have a query,
and then you have
a bunch of other elements,
which are represented
by your keys and your values.
And you want to know which
other elements are actually
relevant in order to compute
the embedding for that query.
So right now, we have only
used tokens, text tokens.
But text tokens, they're
actually vectors.
So if you take those
vectors, and you actually
represent something
else than text--
like for instance,
parts of an image--
the question is,
would the transformer
based on that kind of
input also perform well.
And so here the key
question that I want to ask
is, how can we adapt
our transformer
to work on non-text input.
And for instance, here we can
think of image understanding
input.
So you have some image.
And so it's a traditional
computer vision
task where you want to in which
class this image belongs to.
So you want to know if
having some transformer based
architecture would work
well in that situation.
Well, the answer to
that is, well, first,
in order to adapt
it to this task,
you would take the encoder
parts of the transformer
because in order to understand
what is in an image,
you need to classify
that image in some sense.
So if you remember, if
there is a one model--
and what we saw that was working
very well for classification
was BERT, because
BERT is encoder only.
It computes
meaningful embeddings
that can then be used
for projection purposes
or for classification purposes.
So it's a very natural choice
that here we would have.
So here, we would just keep the
encoder part of the transformer
and then have the self-attention
mechanism come into play
and compute meaningful
embeddings that we could then
project for our relevant task.
And this is exactly what a group
of researchers did back in 2020.
So have you heard of
VIT, vision transformer.
Yeah, no, yeah?
So what I described here
is exactly what they did.
So they took an image.
They divided that
image into patches.
Those patches were
represented by some vectors.
And of course, you have some
kind of position information
that allows you to know where
your patches in the image.
And then you just put it
through the transformer encoder.
So the encoder part
of the transformer.
And you compute the
representation corresponding
to the CLS class,
very similar to BERT.
And you would just project
that representation
over some classes of interest.
And then you would perform your,
I guess, computation like this.
So what that paper found
was that if you train such
a model on a lot of image
data, a lot of image data,
you then outperform these is
traditional convolutional neural
network kind of methods.
And it was kind of
remarkable because.
So why is it remarkable.
Because in the vision case.
So there is this concept
of inductive bias
where you want to gear
your model towards looking
at certain things in order
to deduce the results.
So convolutional neural
networks are a kind of model
that are designed
in a way for you
to look at the image
in some sliding way.
You look at your
image a little bit
like you would look at it
in practice as a human.
And people had hypothesized
that such a bias, such
an inductive bias would actually
make sense for something
like a vision task.
So you contrast that with
the vision transformer, which
is actually letting all parts
of the image attend to one
another, which has, on the other
side, very low inductive bias.
So what this paper showed was if
you give your model enough data,
then it will actually learn
how to classify, I guess,
your images in these classes.
So this was kind of
a remarkable result.
So I think this was
pretty remarkable
and a nice extension
of everything we saw.
So with that in mind,
I want us to just go
through an end to end example of
how you would process an image
and go through that VIT,
so vision transformer,
in order to make
your prediction.
So here, you would take
your favorite image
that you would just
split into patches.
So here, you can think of you
predefining some fixed size
patches.
So here, I would say
3 by 3, let's say.
And then each patch has
some fixed number of pixels.
And then what you do
is for each patch,
you try to have some
vector representation.
So you can think
of each patch as--
so what is the patch.
So it's composed of pixels.
So if each pixel has
three values which
correspond to red,
green, and blue,
then you can find a way to
project those on some lower
dimensional flattened space.
And you can learn how
you would project that
through some kind
of linear layer.
So long story short, you just
find a way to associate a vector
to each of these patches,
which you then represent
every single one of your input.
And then you have, of course,
a special embedding for the CLS
token, which you can
also learn, and you
add the position embedding.
So you do the same for
all of your inputs.
And then very similar
to BERT, Just put that
through your encoder.
Let everyone interact
with everyone.
And then at the end of the
day, what you care about
is a representation of the
input that is meaningful.
So typically, people take
the encoder embedding
of the CLS token.
So the reason why
they take that is one,
because it's a convention.
But the second one
is this CLS token.
So the encoded
embedding is actually
an embedding that has
interacted with all other tokens
through this
self-attention mechanism.
So it has seen everything.
And then you would project
that CLS token encoded
embedding onto some
class through a feed
forward neural network in order
to predict your final class.
So in this case, we know it's
a picture of a Teddy bear.
So here, we would want
the model to classify
this as a Teddy bear.
So far so good?
Does that make sense?
Cool.
So now we know how to process
image input right now.
So another question is, how
would you have your LLM answer
questions about your image,
which is something that you
can do actually nowadays.
If you open ChatGPT,
you can input an image
and ask it questions.
So you would have
two kinds of inputs.
So you would have an image which
we can find a way to represent,
and then the text, which
you now know very well how
to represent with tokens.
So the way you would
allow the model
or let the model
process all of this
is typically as follows-- so
there are a couple of methods.
The first one is the most
common one, which is you just
feed everything as input.
So the image token as input,
the text tokens as inputs.
And you have some representation
to have the model just
know that these are image
tokens and this is text token.
And then you let it
generate an answer
in a decoder only fashion,
autoregressive fashion
exactly like you would do it.
The first method and
a lot of such models
are designed that way.
So there is, for instance,
a very popular open weight,
I believe vision
language model, VLM--
that's what they are called
a model called LAVA--
And this is how they do it.
So they have some encoder
on the image parts
that produces some
tokens that are then
concatenated with text tokens
that are inputs into the LLM.
So that's one method.
The second method,
which is less common,
is to have the images be inputs
at the cross-attention layer.
So here, what you would do
is you have your text inputs.
And then your image inputs,
you don't put it in the inputs.
You actually let it interact
with the text tokens
within the
cross-attention layer.
And this is something
that, for instance, Llama 3
had represented in their paper.
This technique is
typically less common.
The first one is more common.
So I guess what I want
to say is CME 295 focused
on the transformer specifically
in the case of text
to text problems.
So text generation
is all this class.
But we also have the
transformer that was
used for non-text applications.
So here, we saw
image understanding.
So vision
understanding with VIT.
And then we will not have
the time to see this now.
But also for image
generation tasks,
we can also have parts
of the transformer
be used in that architecture.
And so you may hear about
diffusion transformer
or multimodal
that actually rely on the
self-attention mechanism.
And this is actually
not an exhaustive list.
This is also something
that has been
used in other domains like
recommendation speech and so on.
So I guess what I
want you to remember
from this is that transformers
was an architecture that
performed very well for
machine translation tasks.
But then it proved
to perform very well
for other text related tasks.
And it was then
reused in a bunch
of other domains, which also
proved to be quite successful.
So I would just encourage
you, after this class,
to also keep an open mind for
non-text related transformer
applications.
And the ones that
I mentioned here
are maybe just a few first few
pointers into the kind of papers
that you can look at.
Cool.
So here, we said
that transformer
was something that came from the
text world that's also useful
and used in other worlds.
Now I want to tell you
about something else that
was, I guess, used and useful
in the non-text worlds that may
be useful in the text world.
And I want to tell you
about diffusion-based LLMs.
So who has heard
the term diffusion?
Who knows about diffusion?
Yeah.
Cool.
So we will see how we
can apply that to LLMs.
So this is a very trendy topic.
I believe the first paper
started in the early 2020s,
but I guess it's only now that
people are starting to have this
really work.
I just want to start with
the motivation, which
is that up until now, we have
taken for granted the fact
that our LLM is an
autoregressive LLM.
And by autoregressive,
what do I mean by that?
So it takes some input.
And what the LLM tries to do
is to predict the next token.
So given everything so far,
we predict the next token.
We do that, and then
we take that token
that we just predicted,
along with everything
that we have predicted so far.
And then we, again,
predict the next token.
We predict it and we
go again and again,
up until finishing the sequence
with that end of sequence
token, which makes
the generation stop.
So this is a true
autoregressive generation,
as in we take the
input so far in order
to predict the next token.
And then we repeat this
process until the end.
So it's something
that people now
try to give it a name, which
is like autoregressive model
kind of model.
So ARM, if you see this
notation, that's what it means.
The problem with
that kind of paradigm
is that inference time
generation is actually
not something you
can parallelize,
because you always need
what's before in order
to predict the next one.
But I just want to say that
inference time generation is not
parallelizable, but
training is parallelizable.
So if you remember, the
way we do training is we
input all the tokens that
we want our model to predict
and then we let the model
generate tokens out of this.
So basically in a
decoder only setting
you have this causal mask
which lets your model not
cheat if you want and
not use the future ones.
So I just want to say that when
I say that this paradigm is not
parallelizable, I just want
to emphasize on the fact
that it's an inference
time that I'm saying.
Training time, you can actually
parallelize that quite well.
So as I mentioned,
that's one of the reasons
why people have tried to
look at other paradigms.
And in particular, so if
you know about diffusion,
you know that it works very
well for the vision domain.
And so people have tried
adapting this paradigm
for the text generation case.
And so this is a
bunch of screenshots
we took from an announcement
that happened this year.
So for instance,
earlier this year,
there was an experimental text
diffusion model from Google
that they presented during
the I/O event, which
was very impressive because
it led to a lot of speed ups.
And then we have some
different startups.
So Inception is one
of them that made
headlines I believe a couple
of weeks ago, or last week.
No, sorry, a month ago.
That also are
pursuing this route.
So all of that to say
that this direction is
a very trendy and hot
direction that potentially
has a lot of promise.
But the key issue with this
is that text is discrete,
whereas images are continuous.
And we're going to see why that
distinction that I just made
matters.
So I'm going to try
to explain to you what
diffusion is in two minutes.
So in the image world,
in order to generate
an image, what people typically
do is they start from noise,
and then they try to
generate some image.
Now you may wonder,
OK, why noise.
Well, you cannot do something
autoregressive because I guess,
if you were to say, OK,
let's predict the pixels one
at a time, it's just not
tractable because there are many
pixels in an image.
And this is typically not how
you would produce an image.
But some other reasons are
that noise is just something
that you can model very
well with some very
popular distributions.
So Gaussian distribution,
if you about it,
it has very nice properties.
Also, noise is very
easy to sample.
So it's very easy
to start with that.
Noise is also a way for you
to introduce randomness,
because you don't necessarily
want to always produce
the same image.
You want to have, I guess,
choice of generating images
that are slightly
different from one another.
And just mathematically,
it works quite well.
And speaking of
that, the goal is
to learn some
transformation that
would allow you to go from
noise to the target image
distribution.
So all of what I said here
is just reasons for me
to tell you noise
is actually a choice
that is quite
natural to start with
in order to generate an image.
And to give you an analogy,
let's suppose you're a sculptor.
So the person who
does sculptures.
So if you want to
do a sculpture,
you typically start
with some rock.
But then rocks are
different from one another.
They always have things
that are unique to them.
And still, you would focus
on what to remove in order
to obtain the end sculpture.
So you can think of the
rock as being your noise,
and your end result as being
your target data distribution.
So I just want to have
this quote by Michelangelo.
So the sculpture is already
complete within the marble
block.
Before I start my work,
it is already there.
I just have to chisel away
the superfluous material.
The reason why I'm
reading that is you
can have a nice analogy
between what Michelangelo said
and the process of de-noising
the noise to get an image.
So this is all just motivating
how image generation is done.
So you start from noise, and
you want to generate an image.
So the way you do
that for diffusion
is to learn some
transformation that would allow
you to go from noise to image.
So you have two steps.
I mean, you have
more than two steps,
but we have these two main
steps for diffusion models
where you first want to
start from clean images.
And you add noise
gradually until you
obtain some very noisy image.
And then from that, what
diffusion models try to do
is to predict the noise
to remove in order
to obtain the image.
So it's a little bit like
you're the sculpture person.
And you have your rock.
You just want to learn
what pieces of rock
you need to remove in order to
obtain your final piece of art.
So this is what diffusion is.
So it works pretty well
because noise, as I mentioned,
is typically something
that people draw
from a Gaussian distribution.
Gaussian distributions
are mathematically
very well defined, have
a lot of nice properties.
So that's why they work so well.
But now the question
is, how would you
adapt this to the text world.
Because in the text
world, as you know,
we're talking about tokens.
Tokens are discrete.
So there's not this
concept adding noise.
You cannot have that.
So what people have
tried to do was
to find a text equivalent
that would make sense.
And this is what
the current research
points to which is
that noise is to images
what the mask token is to text.
So mask is just a way
for us to just not
have the information coming
from one part of the sequence.
And I just want to go through
the revised 2-step process that
we saw here for text.
So here, for the
forward process,
instead of noising
your input, you
would just have more and more
inputs that would be masked.
So that's the full process.
And at the end, you would
just obtain a sequence
full of masked tokens.
So what you want to do is
to learn some model that
allows you to unmask these
masked tokens in a way that
reconstructs the
original sentence.
So there's some math
that goes into it.
Obviously, in a few
minutes, we will not
have time to go into that.
But I just want to emphasize
on the key idea, which
is you want to do
diffusion, but in a way that
makes sense for text inputs.
And the way it
would make sense is
to consider the noise
for images as being
mask tokens for text input.
Cool.
And so with that
in mind, you have
a bunch of models that
are being released
these days which are called
masked diffusion models, MDM.
So whenever you see MDM, now
you know what kind of model
we're talking about.
So notations are still
not very well defined.
So it may change in the future.
But one other term
you will see out there
is also DLLM,
diffusion based LLM.
And this is what it's doing.
So instead of predicting a token
in an autoregressive fashion one
at a time, what it does
is that at inference time,
it goes from a completely
masked input sequence.
And it tries to predict what
tokens were behind these mask
tokens.
So of course, in a
real life setting,
you would have
some prompts here.
You would have some prompts.
So of course, in order
to predict these answer,
you would have
some conditioning.
So you would tell
your model, OK,
given this prompts you're going
to start with all these mask
tokens.
Just try to predict
what the answer is.
So in case you're having
trouble with the intuition--
so I also had trouble
in the beginning.
Why would it make
sense for texts
to be solved in a
diffusion manner.
Because typically,
when you write,
you write one word at a time.
So one helpful way
to think about this
is let's suppose you
want to write a speech.
So you would not directly write
your speech in a linear way.
You would first
have a rough plan.
You say, OK, I'm going to talk
about this in the first place,
second, third.
You have some kind of drafts.
And then you try to refine what
is in each of these sections.
So you can think of diffusion
as kind of working like this.
So it tries to have a coarse to
find refinement of the outputs
so it can predict things that
are after a certain token that
has not been predicted.
But you can think of
this as being something
that goes from a very drafty
version to a very refined
version.
So that's what I think
about this process.
Hopefully, that's helpful.
And the key advantage here is
that the decoding is now done
in much fewer forward passes,
because previously you
had to do as many forward passes
as there are tokens to predict.
But here for diffusion, you
only need to do as many passes
as there are steps in
your diffusion process,
and the number of steps
is something you can fix.
So the higher the step,
the more high quality
your output is, but it's
typically much lower
than the length of your output.
So that is the core reason why
this model is so much faster
than the autoregressive one.
And of course, we don't
have that much time.
But in case you're
curious, in case
you're interested, after the
final, once you're completely
freed in terms of
things to think of,
just put some references
that could be helpful.
There's a paper that came
out earlier this year
called LLaDA, large language
diffusion model with masking.
Actually, I don't
remember the full acronym.
But it is actually
going through the math
and why the thing that
I just mentioned works.
And then there's a
bunch of other papers
that would also be helpful.
So the links are at
the bottom of the slide
in case you're interested.
And I just want to go
through two last things
before giving it to Shervine.
So first on the advantages
of this new paradigm.
So the first one is the speed.
So as we mentioned, it's
going to be much faster
than traditional
autoregressive models,
especially for outputs
that are longer.
And so some benchmarks, they
even say that it's something
along the lines of 10x faster.
So for cases like coding,
it can be very powerful
because you may have to
do several model calls.
And you as a user, you're just
waiting for that code to happen.
And just having a lower latency
makes a lot of difference.
The other thing is that
the nature of this approach
is actually considering
the text as a whole
in order to make
the predictions.
And so there is a
category of coding tasks
that are called fill in the
middle, which is about trying
to figure out-- you
have a bunch of codes,
and you want to know what's
missing in the middle.
And so fill in the middle.
And diffusion models are
typically better formulated
for these kinds of tasks because
they can consider, I guess,
input from multiple directions.
And that's why this
approach can be probably
something that can be useful
for some applications.
So in terms of the current
work, so these models,
they look great.
What I mentioned
to you looks great.
But the performance was not on
par with the current frontier
models, at least for some time.
But it's something
that may change.
So the papers that
I mentioned, they
are actually posting
performance that
is kind of catching up with the
models that are autoregressive.
So there is some
promise in there.
And then the other
line of work is just
to adapt all the techniques
that people have come up with.
Like for instance,
reasoning chains,
how do you adapt that
for diffusion, and so on.
There are so many techniques
that are intrinsically
more better suited for
autoregressive kinds of models
that can be adapted for that.
And that's what
people are working on.
So long story short,
what we saw was
that things we saw in this class
could be used in other domains.
For instance, we saw
the vision transformer
that was boring the transformer
for vision related tasks.
But we also saw that
things from other domains
could also be used
in the text world.
And that's what we saw
with diffusion LLMs.
And so this is probably, of
course, a subset of everything
that's happening.
And so with that, I
think we're concluding
our second item of our menu.
And I'm going to just
give it to Shervine.
Thank you, Afshine.
And with that, welcome to
the last part of the season
finale of CME 295.
And as Afshine mentioned, now
is the time for some closing
thoughts and see
what we can get away
from this class and the concepts
that are neighboring to it.
So first, Afshine went
through the concept
of diffusion and images.
And we saw some similarities.
We could draw with text.
And now we're going to see
what kinds of inspirations
have both modalities
taken from each other.
And we're going to see that
actually, a lot of things
can be reused.
So the first thing
that I want to mention
in terms of what has been
reused is the architecture part.
So Afshine mentioned
these diffusion concept
that was born in
the field of images,
but that was taken
for text, and was
able to yield a lower latency
like higher speed ups, which
is great when you're an user.
So this was one
example of a win.
And then on the other
direction, traditionally, images
have been dealing with
convolutions mostly
as model architecture type.
But these papers saw that
replacing convolutions
with transformers was very good,
even yielding better results.
So all these latest
diffusion-based papers
in the field of images
typically use transformers.
And here, I'm linking
one of the papers
that Afshine already
briefly went through.
But not only is it the
architecture side that
is the subject of pollination
between these modalities,
you could even
think of other kinds
of components like the input.
And for this one,
I want to mention
the example of DeepSeek OCR.
So I don't know if you've
heard of this paper.
It just came out very recently.
And contrary to what
the name suggests,
so OCR stands for optical
character recognition.
And it's usually a field
that tries to converts
some scanned image into text.
But actually, that paper
doesn't boast some improvements
on the OCR task itself.
Rather, it showed
that you could learn
some function that
reconstructs text tokens based
on vision tokens.
And not only on vision tokens.
On very few vision tokens.
So it showed that
the representation
power of patches of images
as tokens was very strong.
And you have some researchers
that bring some rationale to it
like Hey Tokenizers are
not the best tool anyway.
And the things in patches
convey the meaning of texts
already with the
example of emojis
and so on that you
would otherwise
need to represent with
way more tokens in text.
And then another example
I want to mention
is even when you look
inside the architectures,
some of the tricks can be reused
and adapted in each field.
So here, I'm
mentioning the example
of rope, which Afshine
mentioned in the recap that
was used in texts to represent
the relative position of tokens.
And in the case of images
or even multi-modal setting,
where you have the presence
of both text and image within
the architecture, you're
able to adapt that trick
by reformulating it in 2D.
So here the figure shows how
you can attribute rope positions
in the two degrees, and how you
could place text tokens such
that the relative computation
of position still makes sense.
And even beyond
that, I would say
that the ongoing research for
transformers is very much alive
and people are still
figuring out all the details
that we're working with today.
And you see refinements
all the time
coming in terms of new papers.
So it's something that
is still developing.
And you can look at it
from multiple angles.
One is each of these design
decisions that we've had,
they are still
being iterated on.
So I'm listing a few
items here as an example.
So one is the optimizer side.
You might be familiar with the
Adam optimizer and its update
rule, which has been
popular for quite some time.
And it seems that state is being
challenged with newer papers.
So I referenced here
the Kimi K2 paper
that came out a few
months ago that introduces
a new kind of
optimizer called Muon.
And the latest version
of that MuonClip
seems to be a potential
candidate for this optimizer
to become the new standard.
So this field, even as basic as
it can be, is still developing.
But it's not only
the optimizer side.
You also have the
topic of normalization,
where Afshine mentioned
that the difference
between the original
transformer paper
and what you see
today in LLM papers,
you don't have the same kind
of normalization anymore.
In the past, you had post norm.
But now you have pre norm, which
brings the normalization earlier
on in the layer.
But beyond that design choice of
the location of normalization,
you even have the type of
normalization that changes.
So the transformer
paper used layer norm.
But these days, you might see
other kinds of normalization
techniques like RMS norm which
uses less parameters and others.
So the theory behind
it is not set just yet.
So you have other
kinds of parameters.
I've seen mentioned the
grouped query attention paper.
And you see these days in LLM
papers, not a fixed design.
Rather every paper adopts
their own technique.
Sometimes you see one kind of
attention used as a given layer,
but then it switches,
and different papers take
different design decisions.
So it's not set in stone.
Then you also have
activation functions.
So traditionally, in deep
learning, a lot of emphasis
was put on ReLU,
which is a very simple
and used worked very well.
But in the world
of LLMs, the shift
was towards ReLU like activation
functions, but not exactly ReLU.
So you had a Gaussian
error, linear units
you had other kinds.
And the research there
is still ongoing.
So you still see new activation
functions coming in now
and then.
And then you have
also whether to take
the design option of considering
the LLM as an MOE or not.
And even the number
of layers of your LLM
and other hyperparameters
like number of heads.
Size of the number of units
in the FFN, all of that
is still up for debate in
terms of design decisions.
So it's not fixed.
And then another area of
research I want to mention
is the data part,
which is crucial.
So the first LLMs, they enjoyed
a relatively clean state
of things because you
could scrape the internet
and hope for a lot of data that
was for sure human generated.
So you could learn these
patterns from, quote unquote,
a high quality source, even
though it's not in high quality
format when you look at
typical internet data,
but it was still
generated by human.
So these days, the
state has changed.
You type anything you want in
your favorite search browser.
Chances are the first results
are 80% LLM generated.
So are we doomed?
Maybe not, because actually
you see the development more
and more work in data curation.
So in the past, you would
just scrape the whole internet
and train next token
prediction on it.
But now, you have more and more
of this work of curating data
sets of interest.
And you have companies
that work on it.
And you have the emergence
of newer fine tuning modes.
So in the past, you had
pre-training and then fine
tuning.
Now you have pre-training,
mid training, and fine tuning.
And the mid training part trains
still on a large corpus of data,
but higher quality.
So people are finding
ways around it.
And I would say the
picture is not all grim,
but it's just that we need to
do more work in order to have
meaningful data at hand.
And the paper that is linked
at the bottom of the slide
is dealing with the
phenomenon of what
if you were training
on LLM generated data
and it's talking about a
concept called model collapse.
And it says that LLM generated
text is typically less diverse.
So the data distribution that
you would see at training time
changes and it leads to
less meaningful learning
at training time, which
is why it's typically bad.
And it motivates the need for
more work on the data part.
OK, nice.
And then even taking a step
back on the very architecture
we've been using all along.
Is it the best one?
it's not clear.
So that itself is
an area of research.
And future
breakthroughs might come
from redesigning
this architecture.
So in the past few years,
a lot of the research
that we have seen has been
on improving benchmarks
even more each time.
So you have a set of benchmarks.
Everyone tries to
get the best results.
So it's a natural
trend because you
want to have more
and more powerful
models that fulfill
all your use cases.
But let's say we reach a
point where all the use
cases we care about are solved.
Then what?
So I think we're going
to see the emergence
of these second border
of the Pareto frontier,
where we care most about
making predictions from LLM
cost effective and
still very high quality.
So we see this emergence of
smaller and smaller LLMs.
I think it has been
dubbed small language
models, SLM, in the literature.
And typically, you hear
sometimes LLM providers
say that they lose money even
on the highest tier plans.
So I think it reflects the fact
that you need to be smarter
in the compute that you spend
for serving LLM queries at test
time.
And I think this will
motivate more and more
this line of research
in the coming years.
And then there is another
area that we've not
touched on at all in this class,
which is the hardware part.
So typically, the kind of device
that you use to train these LLMs
are GPUs, which are
great at one thing--
matrix multiply.
But the thing is, we've kept
these kinds of architectures
to train our models, even though
the architecture doesn't only
need matrix multiplies as
a foundational atomic unit
of compute, the self-attention
world and the transformer world
has all these special needs.
The qk transpose part we saw
was actually very expensive,
which has motivated papers
such as flash attention
to, as I've seen mentioned,
actually forego of some
of the data for the sake of
not doing too much movements
on the memory side, even
if it meant recomputing
the same things afterwards.
And then a lot of work
has been on optimizing
where the flow of memory
within the GPU resides.
And this shows that maybe you
need a more optimized hardware
architecture in order to
solve these use cases.
So there is a recent
paper that came out
that actually encodes
all of these operations
as part of the hardware.
So in the past,
the core operation
that the GPU was great
at is matrix multiply.
And based on it, you try to
build all of the input output
that you want.
But here this paper that came
out, I think, in September
shows a proof of
concept where you
can do all of these
computations as a side
effect of implementing input
and outputs with analog signals.
So you have all of these
computations that are embedded
as part of the hardware.
And based on pulses as input
that simulates your array
values, these
hardware architectures
have some physical
properties, you
could think of a Kirchhoff
law in the field of, I think,
intensity.
You can add them up.
And it uses properties like this
to have what you need as inputs
and just read out the
results as output.
So when the paper simulated
this kind of architecture,
they observed, without too
much surprise quite a bit
of improvement
both on the latency
and energy saving
parts both explained
because you don't need to do
the computations yourself.
You just get them as a side
effect of your hardware.
Now I want to take
a step back and look
at our users, at our
use cases of LLMs today
and what could lie ahead, what
could be the most exciting
for you.
So today, we've seen
that in just a few years,
I think it has become
quite important to know how
to use them if you want
to speed up everything
you do in your daily life.
So a few lectures ago, we
talked about the coding case
where do you have all these
AI systems coding tools
that enable you
to turn into code,
some natural language prompts.
So you just ask for
something and it
will help you do that task
with a so-called agent mode.
And this is just something that
you would do as an engineer.
But even beyond that, other use
cases are deeply impacted by it
because you have
a lot of problems
that today can be turned
into a text to query or text
to code problem.
So you could think of even the
visualization world, you could--
So for example, there was a
launch from Google recently
that showed that you could
generate visualizations
on the fly based
on some principles.
And this is already
changing quite a bit
the picture of what
you can do today.
Something else that I think is
used by most people actually
today when using
these chatbots is
like being a general
assistant, so you
ask about common facts
and all the facts
that it has learned at
training time becomes useful.
It browses the web more
efficiently than you
and converts into
natural language
the things that you care about.
But then there are
also other domains
that were impacted by it.
So you could think
creativity where
a lot of jobs such as
marketing or others
rely on getting something
out of a blank page.
And usually, if you
start from a draft,
it's much easier to get
something done rather than just
thinking of it from scratch.
So it's used as a net here.
And also, one use case that
I've seen in class that I think
is great that some of you do--
sometimes I talk
about something,
or I've seen talks
and I see people typing on
ChatGPT related concepts.
And I think it's very smart to
do that because brainstorming
the concepts that you learn
is great for actually grasping
the concepts of interest.
And getting that
early feedback loop
is very useful for learning.
So I have a lot of hopes
regarding how great of a time
it is for you to learn as
opposed to maybe having
a nice time maybe 10 years ago.
So yeah, keep doing that.
And I think it will
be a growing use case.
So looking forward.
So I said, tomorrow
on the slide,
but actually two
days ago, there was
a launch that went in the
direction of what I was thinking
about, which is all the agentic
things that we talked about,
there are still
very much confined
into people that
about the field.
Everyday people, they
wouldn't typically use,
quote unquote,
agentic workflows.
So I think one
field of development
that we will see more
and more is all these use
cases being democratized.
So people can now create things
that can be useful to them
with easier mediums, just
natural language, no need
to code moving forward to later.
So all these AI assisted
coding that I was mentioning,
you could think of it as
helping you browse the internet
in a very natural fashion.
So it seems, right now,
when you just execute tasks,
you're way too microscopic
in what you do.
And this is typically what AI
assistant could help you do.
So there are recent
product launches
that reflect this growing
interest, such as ChatGPT's
Atlas.
So I think it
launched in October.
I don't know if they released
some public number on usage.
I suspect it's still
timid because you still
have challenges when
it comes to security.
Anyone could inject
some bad prompt in there
and maybe exfiltrate
things from you.
But I'm sure the community
will come up with more ways
to get around it.
So in the past, you
had HTTPS, for example,
to say that the
connection was secure.
Maybe tomorrow, you'll
have some certificate
that will guarantee that a site
website is safe for AI assistant
browsing and looking
even at a higher level,
maybe just browsing on your
desktop or your mobile phone
at the LLM level.
At the OS level, might be
something that the LLM can help.
So when we talked
about agents, we
mentioned how
non-reliable it could
be because as you have
more and more steps,
the probability for
a failure increases.
And stabilizing predictions
is something of interest.
And even in the
longer run, I think
one test that we can have in
mind as to how far we've come
is whether the common
use case of having
a customer service that is
served by AI is truly useful.
So I don't about you, but
every time I have a problem,
and I'm on the phone, and I
hear some AI assistant, maybe
LLM powered robot, I'm kind
of quick, quick, quick,
I want a human, I
don't want that.
And I think it shows
how hard this space is,
the space of problems is because
human has way more dimensions
of value that an
LLM could bring.
So empathy, groundedness,
there are some things
that you and we perceive
as things that make sense,
even though they're not
in our system prompts.
So I think there are hard
problems to solve there.
And even moving forward,
there are some key challenges
that we have with the
current architecture.
So we saw during
the class that you
had to go through a
training process that
went to fix some weights.
But these weights are
not changing afterwards.
And we use tricks such as RAG or
tools to get around this issue.
But could we think of a system
that learns continuously?
I think that is
an open question.
Then there is a topic
of hallucinations
which I put into quotation
marks because I'm not sure
if it's fair to say that the LLM
hallucinates just because we've
trained the LLM to predict
the next token by nature,
not map statements to facts.
So hallucinating
is, in some sense,
a core design choice
of these LLMs.
Personalization,
interpretability,
safety the list goes on.
Now I want to
briefly cover how you
can exercise this muscle of
staying up to date from now.
So you have archive
that usually contains
all these greatest
and latest papers
that you can take a look at.
Of course, the
venues like NeurIPS
right now are great to
highlight some papers.
And then I highly encourage
you, besides the papers,
looking at the
associated codebases
that the authors provide.
So right now, it's a
commonplace to just provide
the implementation of
what you're proposing.
And I think it's very insightful
to learn the concepts.
And there is a paper with
code that existed in the past.
And that has been replaced by
HuggingFace trending papers,
which I think is a good place
to take a look at the latest
methods.
And then on the
social network side,
Twitter or X has a lot of the
latest that is often discussed.
So you have a strong
community there.
And if you have an account
on that social media,
you have a lot of great people
to follow to stay updated.
But also, you have
resources on YouTube,
which highlight on Yannic
Kilcher, which I think
was the first YouTuber to cover
the transformer paper back
in 2017 in great detail.
And I think some
of these YouTubers,
they're very good at talking
through papers in great detail.
And another highlight
is Andrej Karpathy,
who was at Stanford
about 10 years ago.
And he's, I think, one of
the best educators out there.
So I highly
recommend his videos.
And you have company
blogs that are also great.
And this study guide that we
associated with the class,
so we've had it for this year.
And what we'll try to
do in the coming years
is try to keep it updated
at least on a yearly basis.
So you can consider
this resource
as maybe some companion.
And we've got the chance
to collaborate with experts
around the world to make it
available in other languages,
in case you're interested.
And taking a step
back, just want
to say that Afshine and I
were very grateful to teach
this class this quarter.
Thank you so much for coming
here on Friday evening, which
is quite telling, because
Friday evening is usually
a time for fun,
not for lectures.
And also now, I
think it's probably
your last lecture
of the whole quarter
because next week is finals.
So yeah, thank you for
coming and for asking
all these great questions.
You were one of the
reasons why this class was
so great and interactive.
Also, thank you to the folks who
are watching online from home.
I was one of you
eight years ago.
I would almost never
go to class, always
watching lectures from
home, from a cozy place.
I hope the lectures
were entertaining
and that you got
something from it.
And I couldn't conclude without
bringing our favorite Teddy bear
one last time.
Thanking you all
for your attention
and wishing you all the best.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]